<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Encoding P.NUMBER</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Not intended for publication.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>The Royall Master</title>
               <author>James Shirley</author>
               <date>1638</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <sp>
            <l>I onely shall bleed inward, and my life</l>
            <l> Remove it selfe like a faire apparition</l>
            <l> That vanishes to th'eye, and with lesse noise</l>
            <l> Then a calme Summers evening, but when I</l>
            <l> Am dead, tis not impossible, some may</l>
            <l> Report <name rend="italic">Theodosia</name> was but revish'd from me;</l>
            <l> Feare of a brothers anger, and the tricke</l>
            <l> Of polliticke states, that marry to knit power</l>
            <l> Not hearts, did force her to <name rend="italic">Herares</name> armes,</l>
            <l> Whilst I, torne from the branch where I once grew,</l>
            <l>Travell I know not whether in the aire.</l>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Riviero.</speaker>
            <l> I begin</l>
            <l> To thinke him worth some pitty.</l>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Montalto.</speaker>
            <l>Into what</l>
            <l>Vaine thing would the severe apprehension</l>
            <l>Of greefe transforme us? coward, let the <name rend="italic">Duke</name></l>
            <l> Move with all amorous haste to his delight,</l>
            <l>And glory in the hope of his faire bride,</l>
            <l> Mine by the gift of heaven, and hearts, but all</l>
            <l> My flowers grow dully on their stalkes, and wither;</l>
            <l> Let her gay Paranimphs with rosie Chaplets,</l>
            <l> Which will take all their colour from her blush,</l>
            <l>Attend on <name rend="italic">Theodosia</name> to the Temple,</l>
            <l> While as they goe, no rude winde shall be heard,</l>
            <l>But so much breath of heaven as gently may</l>
            <l> Lifting their loose haire up, whisper my wrong</l>
            <l> To every Virgins care, let them be married,</l>
            <l> Knit hands, and plight a ceremonious faith;</l>
            <l> Let all the triumphs waste, let them be wasted,</l>
            <l> And night it selfe brib'd with a thousand formes</l>
            <l> Of mirth and Revells, till the night grow faint</l>
            <l> And pale with watching,</l>
            <l> Invite to bed, yet there he shall enjoy</l>
            <l> But <name rend="italic">Theodosiaes</name> body, and not that</l>
            <l> As his faire thoughts expect, perhaps the conquest</l>
            <l> Of one whom he loved better.</l>
         </sp>
         <stage place="right" type="exit"> Exit <name>Montalto</name>.</stage>
         <stage place="centre" type="enter">Enter <name>Duke</name>.</stage>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Riviero.</speaker>
            <l> How was that.</l>
         </sp>

         <fw rend="italic" type="catch" place="bottom-right"><name rend="italic">Duke</name>.</fw>
         <pb/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
